OP--
それは 調査中です
だが いったいどうしたことだ
な こ これは 日の本の地図
This map is of the Land of the Rising Sun.
本字幕由诸神字幕组（kamigami.org）制作，仅供交流学习，禁止用于任何商业用途
日听:东吾 king  翻译:念白白 poopy   校对:木落 时间轴:wcaster
But what is this?
We're investigating that.
This wall is so hard to climb...
まったく なんと登りづらい塀なのだ
つまり これは俺に対しての嫌がらせだな
Is this their way of hazing me?
それにしても この築地塀造りがなってないぞ
And it's poorly made, too.
そもそも 築地塀とは
Originally, this style of wall was
古くは御所 もしくは有職の家柄のみに許された塀であって
only allowed on the Imperial Palace
or other noble households.
息がしづらい 服が重い
It's hard to breathe and these
clothes are so heavy!
自由に動くこともかなわんではないか
I can barely move.
やはり 俗世は 俺の敵のようだな
I guess the world of commoners
just isn't for me.
ちなみに 俗世とは世の中という意味であって
For what it's worth, the world of commoners
refers to the normal world.
まぁ 俗と世間という意味もあるが
Not that I would ever want
俺はそんな安っぽい使い方はしたくないのであって
to associate myself with
something common, anyway.
だが まぁ 今は許してやろう
But for now, I'll forget that.
俺には 大義があるがゆえ
I have a duty!
I already told you!
だから
あんたは 無涯さんのこと何にもわかってないのよ
You don't understand anything about Mugai-san.
いえ しかし 火鉢殿
But, Hibachi-dono...
月島 いい
Listen, Tsukishima...
無涯さんの一番の魅力はあの孤高の強さなの
The best thing about Mugai-san
is his solitary strength!
Oh, Mugai-san.
ああ 無涯さん
いいえ それは少し違います 火鉢殿
No...
I don't think that's accurate, Hibachi-dono.
無涯殿のすばらしさは孤高などではなく
It's the way he can make
anyone seeing him feel safe...
見る者の不安をかき消す
イチャコラしおって 役人のくせに
Look at those two flirting.
Government officials shouldn't flirt!
まぁ いい
It doesn't matter.
これなら 目的の蟲文庫へ行くのはたやすいな
This will make it easy to reach
my goal, the Insect Archives.
ふふふん　行くぞ
Here I go.
俺自らが10年ぶりにこうして外へ出てやったのだ
For the first time in ten years,
I've ventured outside in person.
やってみせる すべては知識のためにのぅ…
I can do this!
It's all for the sake of knowledge.
I told you
だ～か～ら
違うって言ってんでしょうが
you're wrong!
Hey, who's that?
ねぇ ちょっと  そいつ 誰
えっ？ おっ なんと
What?
能面をつけているではないですか
He's wearing a Noh mask!
そうじゃなくて　不法侵入者でしょうが
No, not that!
I mean he's an intruder!
「お面の下のイケメン　長福丸」
the Mask: Nagatomimaru
The Hot Guy Beneath
I hate commoners...
まったく 俗世はひどい
人にケガをさせておいてそのうえ不審者扱い
You hurt me and then
treat me like an intruder?
The hearts of men have fallen so far.
人心の荒廃もついに ここまできたか
You should be ashamed!
恥を知れ ちなみに 人心の荒廃とは
By hearts of men, I don't mean
these two specifically,
人心 すなわち世間の人の考え方
but the general—
なに ぶつぶつ言ってんのよ不審者
What are you mumbling about, intruder?
あの  なぜ この奉行所に不法に侵入を
Um, why did you sneak into the Magistrate?
人にものを尋ねるときはまず 名乗るべきだろう
When you ask someone something, you need to name yourself first.
おお これは失礼
Oh, excuse me!
自分は 月島仁兵衛と申します
I am Tsukishima Jinbei!
I am Nagatomimaru.
俺は 長福丸
So what are you doing here, Nagatomimaru-kun?
で 長福丸君
キミは 何のために ここへ
蟲のすべてを知るためだ
I want to know everything about bugs.
おぉ 俺が その気になれば
If I wish, I can get information
and documents of any kind!
どのようなジャンルの書物も知識も手に入れることができる
史書 伝承録 禅書 随筆 書簡集　紀行文 仏典 武道書 礼法書
Historical records, legends, Zen texts,
diaries, letters, travelogues,
Buddhist texts, treatises on war,
etiquette, medicine, mathematics,
医書 和算 天文 本草 はては蘭学にいたるまで
astronomy, herbalism and even foreign texts.
ありとあらゆる すべてをな
From every obtainable text...
お前たちが相手にしている蟲についても
I have read accounts of the insects you fight.
さまざまな書物を読み漁ってきた
くだらぬ町民のうわさ話や体験談を集めた娯楽本
Pulp texts recounting rumors and encounters
between townspeople and insects.
更に 町なかに出回ることのない秘密裏の報告書
And even secret reports which are
never released to the public!
Well? Are you impressed?
どうだ 驚いたか
はい すばらしい博学 おみそれしました
Yes, I am terribly impressed by your knowledge!
何 こいつ オタク？
Is he an otaku?
よいか  すべての物事は知識でカタがつくようになっているのだ
Excellent!
Knowledge can solve any problem.
But...
だが なぜ百年前に突如として巨大蟲が現れたのか
No book has told me why the insects
suddenly appeared a century ago.
それは どのような書物にも載ってはいなかった
俺は知りたい  知らねばならぬ 知識こそ俺の大義
I want to know! I must know!
Knowledge is everything to me!
That's why I've come to the common
world that's filled with enemies.
だから 俺は敵だらけの俗世にやってきた
どのような邪魔立てがあろうとこの蟲奉行所の書物庫
No matter what stands in my way,
I must get to the Insect Archives,
蟲文庫に行かねばならぬ
the records of the Insect Magistrate!
Wh-What resolve!
なんという 熱い覚悟
少しぐらい 見せてさしあげればよいのでは
Couldn't we show him a little?
えーと 悪いけど
Um, I'm sorry but this place is off-limits.
ここは一般人は立ち入り禁止なんだよ ごめんね
Sorry.
ええ なんでだよ
Why? That's mean!
ひっでえ 調べさせてくれてもよいではないか 小役人
You could just let me have a look, couldn't you?
はぁ？ なんで？
Huh? Why?
素性もわからない変人なんかダメに決まってるでしょ
You're just some weirdo.
And I don't like the fact that
you wear a Noh mask
だいたい
人としゃべんのに能面なんかつけてるのが気に入らないのよ
when you talk to people.
やめっ
My face...
顔 ひどいよ
That's mean!
僕の顔 返してよ
Give me back my face!
He's really hot...
めちゃめちゃイケ顔じゃん
I've seen that face somewhere before...
あの顔 どこかで
なんて失礼な女だ 人の顔を奪うなんて
How rude! To steal someone's face!
俺に対する嫌がらせだな絶対 そうだ
I know that you did that because you hate me!
あ だから 小役人は
That's why I hate petty officials.
He got annoying when he put his mask on again.
うわっ 面つけたら また ウザくなった
なんで面なんか つけてんだか
Why do you wear a mask, anyway?
ふん 人間はすぐ嘘をつく
Humans are liars.
誰も 俺のことなんかわかってないくせに
No one understands me.
そろそろ 会合の時間なんでね
I have a meeting...
So I'll be going.
これで失礼するよ 仁兵衛君 家まで送ってあげて
Jinbei-kun, see him home.
へっ おとがめなしで
We're not going to punish him?
まぁ 未遂だし
He hasn't done anything.
では まいりましょう 長福丸殿
Let's go, Nagatomimaru-dono.
いやだ
No! I am going to Insect Archives!
俺は 蟲文庫に行くんだ
Here, Tsukishima.
ほら 月島 さっさと送り届けなさい
Take him home.
Okay!
はい
Insect Archives
Seal
長福丸殿 ところでお宅はどちらですか？
Nagatomimaru-dono, where do you live?
あぁ  おぬし 知っておるか
By the way, did you know
町奉行所の与力同心を八丁堀と呼ぶことがあるがな
that some ranks of Magistrate
are known as "Hacchoubori"
あれは 八丁堀に居住地があるからなのだ
because their barracks are in Hacchoubori?
ちなみに与力は朝一番の女湯に入れるのだ
They're also allowed in the women's
bath early in the morning.
なんと なんと　長福丸殿の知識にかける情熱には
What?
I am very moved by your passion for knowledge!
本当に感動いたします
長福丸殿
Nagatomimaru-dono?
おい 下ろせ
Let me down.
え？ いや しかし
But...
いいから下ろせと言ってるだろうが
I said put me down.
あ はい 直ちに
Yes... Right away.
Um...
あのぉ
そのような目で俺を欺こうとしてもムダだ
You can't deceive me with those eyes!
おぬしだって　心のなかでは俺をバカにしているのだろう
In your heart, you also think
I'm stupid, don't you?
もう よい あとは一人で帰る
Enough!
I'll go the rest of the way alone!
し しかし 自分はお送りするよう　命じられている
But I was ordered to take you back...
そんなもの知るか
I don't care!
The first time in ten years I go outside,
and I end up with nothing.
まったく 10年ぶりに外に出たというのに
結局 何も得られずとは
やはり俗世は敵だらけ
The common world is full of enemies.
二度と外など出てやるものか
I'm never going outside again.
た 助けて くれ
S-Save me...
助けて
Save me...
Yabuka
Night Mosquito
いかんな
Oh, no.
どうやら俺は書物を読みふけりながら 寝てしまったようだ
It appears I've fallen asleep
while reading my books.
夢だな これは
This is a dream.
実物の蟲もさもあろうというリアルな夢だな
I bet the bug in this dream
looks just like a real one.
思えばおかしいことだらけであった
When I think about it,
this has been a strange night.
この俺が小娘に小突かれたり
A little girl yelling at me, a tiny boy
carrying me and now this bug?
ちんちくりんの武士に担がれたり
おまけにこのような蟲が現れたり
It has to be a dream.
まさに夢物語だな
Wait!
待て
Are you okay?
ご無事ですか
長福丸殿も大事はないですか
Nagatomimaru-dono, are you hurt?
He's fast!
こいつ  速い
I see, I see...
なるほど なるほど
This is very realistic.
これは 先日 読んだ蟲捕物の浮世草子そっくりだ
Just like paintings I've seen of bug-slaying.
本当によくできた夢だ
What a dream.
夢ならば さっさと退治してしまえ
If it's a dream, get rid of that thing!
Th-That's impossible...
そっ そんなバカな やはり 夢
It must be a dream.
N-No one in reality would shed blood for me.
そっ そもそもこんな俺のために 血を流す奴が現実にいるはずがない
Only in a dream could anyone fight that monster.
第一 夢物語以外で人間があんな化け物と渡り合えるものか
Nagatomimaru-dono, I'm sorry,
but I have a request.
長福丸殿 申し訳ありませんが　一つ頼みがあります
長福丸殿の豊富な知識に基づいて
Please use your vast stores of knowledge
to tell me how to defeat this bug.
あの蟲の攻略法を ぜひ ご教示ください
What? Why would I do that?
ちょ ちょっと待て なんで 俺が
I'm sorry to ask,
情けない話ですが 長福丸殿の知識に頼るしか 手だてがないのです
but I've no other means of winning this battle.
But...
し…しかしだな
自分が昆虫のことは何でも知っているが
I know everything about insects,
but not about monsters.
化けもののような蟲のこととなると
まだそれほど
大丈夫です
Don't worry!
I believe in your passion for knowledge!
長福丸殿の知識にかける情熱を　信じていますから
そんな　信頼しきった目で俺を見るな
Impossible...
Don't look at me with those trusting eyes.
I... I... I'm not like that.
俺は…俺は違うんだ
そんな目で見られるほどたいしたやつじゃない
I'm not worthy of being looked at that way.
長福丸様はだめだなぁ
Nagatomimaru-sama is no good.
あ　殿と比べたらとても…
Especially compared to His Lordship.
やはり本命は次男の…
The second son will probably be the heir...
おい　長福丸様だぞ
It's Nagatomimaru-sama.
いや　さすがお世継ぎとして頼もしい限りでございます
What a splendid heir you will make!
皆嘘つき
Everyone is a liar.
本当は誰も俺に期待なんかしておらぬし
No one thinks I'm "splendid."
尊敬もしておらぬ
No one respects me.
敬っているのは俺の身分だけのくせに
The only thing they respect is my position.
そんな時俺は　書庫で一冊の本に一つの文書に出会った
And then, I found a book in the storeroom.
徒然草第十三段
The thirteenth volume of Essays in Idleness.
灯火の下で読書に没頭し
Beneath the light,
I focus on reading, and it feels like
the story's characters are my friends.
本に出てくる人々をまるで友のように思う
Yoshida Kenko
何よりの楽しみだ
It becomes my life's greatest joy.
この一節を目にした時　涙が溢れた
When I read this passage,
tears came to my eyes.
一人で生きてもいいんだよ
"It's okay to be alone."
I felt like the book was telling me this.
そう書物に優しく言われた気がした
その時から　嘘をつかない書物の知識だけを
Books don't lie,
so I decided then that they
would be my only friends.
唯一の友としていくことを　決めた
そして俺は無情で嘘つきなこの世を まともに見ることをやめたのだ
And thus, I turned my gaze from
the ephemeral, deceptive world.
Don't worry!
心配ご無用　長福丸殿のご教示を賜るまで
Until you can share your wisdom with me,
この月島仁兵衛　戦いぬいて見せます
I will keep fighting!
人とのかかわりを捨て　こんな面をかぶった俺を
I abandoned my relationships with my
fellow men and donned this mask,
and you still believe in me?
お前は信じているのか
This must be true!
やはり　これは夢である
長福丸殿の知識にかける情熱には
I am very moved by your passion for knowledge!
本当に感動いたします
夢だけに霞がかかって　周りが何も見えん
Since it's a dream, my vision is getting hazy,
and I can't see anything.
だが　それでもいい
But that's fine...
Even if it's only a dream,
I still want to help him.
夢でもいいから　こいつに応えてやる
思考しろ　分析しろ　俺の知識を腐らせるな
Think! Analyze!
Don't let your knowledge go to waste.
消えた
It disappeared?
あれだ
That's it!
Damn it, where did it go?
くっそ　どこへ消えた
Jinbei, was it?
仁兵衛ってやな
Nagatomimaru-dono!
長福丸殿
俺の知識を頼るとは　なかなか気に入ったぞ
I'm glad to see you decided to
make use of my knowledge.
What is this smoke?
この煙は？
これはヨモギや萱を燻した煙で
This smoke is from thatch and mugwort.
It's used to repel a certain type of insect.
ある蟲を駆除するために使うのだが
It should at least slow a giant insect down.
巨大蟲相手でも少しは動きを止められよう
Jeez, I was just about to get some sleep!
もう　こっちは気持ちよく寝ようとしてたのに
I'll get that bug for interrupting my sleep.
ったく　蟲のやつ睡眠不足の恨みだ
今だ　仁兵衛
Now, Jinbei!
はい
Yes!
Always be ready for a fight!
常住戦陣
Yay!
And then,
その時　仁兵衛はこう言ったのだ
Jinbei said, "Please share
your knowledge with me!"
俺に知恵を貸して欲しいとな
はい　とても頼もしかったですよ　長福丸殿
Yes, you were wonderful, Nagatomimaru-dono!
そうであろう　そうであろう
Wasn't I?
いいぞ　日本一
The most brilliant man in Japan!
That's the tenth time I've heard that!
十回目よ　このくだり
Did you see how brilliant I am, girl?
見たか　小娘　俺の知識の偉大さを
この役立たずが
You useless girl!
なっ　こいつ
Y-You little...
Very well.
よし　仕方ない　知恵足らずのお前に力を貸してやろう
I shall share my knowledge, as you are ignorant.
はっ？何言ってるの？
What are you talking about?
大体誰の許可があってここに？
Who said you could be here, anyway?
いいじゃねぇか
Aw, come on.
今日はなかなか満足であった
Today was a splendid day.
よし　明日もここに来てやるか
I know! I'll come back tomorrow.
仁兵衛にはもっといろいろ俺の知識を伝えんとな
I must share more of my knowledge with Jinbei.
This really does seem like a dream...
まったく　本当に夢物語のようだな
Partying somewhere I've never been,
この俺が他の誰かと
こんな見知らぬ場所で
and with people I don't know.
このように騒ぎ倒すとは…
夢ではなく　リアルに
It isn't a dream. It's real.
Oh, Jinbei...
仁兵衛
Well, you see...
その…何だ
感謝ぐらいはしてやるぞ
I am grateful, somewhat.
Foolishness!
くだらん　せっかく蟲奉行所にいるというのに
I've finally made it into the Insect Magistrate.
俺は一体　何をやっている
This is the chance of a lifetime!
The Insect Archives are right before me...
まさに千載一遇のチャンスだというのに
What wonderful knowledge must lie within!
蟲文庫がすぐそこではないか
It must be as great as the Momijiyama archives.
何とも素晴らしい知識の量だ
紅葉山文庫に勝るともおとらぬ
こ　これは蟲の生態に関する書物
This book is about the insect's life cycle.
こっちは蟲を扱う特殊器具についての文献だ
Here's a book about special
weapons for fighting them.
Records of the Magistrate!
蟲方の記録も
What is this?
これは…
I don't know this crest.
And that makes me angry.
見知らぬ紋どころだな
俺が知らない紋どころというだけで許せん
It's very tightly wound.
随分入念に縛ってあるな
What a pain.
面倒臭いやつめ
んなっ　こ　これは　日の本の地図
This map is of the Land of the Rising Sun.
But what is this?
だが　一体どうしたことだ
それは調査中です
We are investigating that...
Tokugawa Ieshige-sama.
徳川家重様
江戸城であなた様をお見かけしたことを
I finally remembered seeing you in Edo castle.
ようやく思い出しました
You...
お前…
八代将軍吉宗様がご長男
The eldest son of the eighth
shogun, Yoshimune-sama.
Tokugawa Ieshige-sama, the next shogun.
次期将軍徳川家重様
おい　与力　これは何だ
What is this, magistrate officer?
Ieshige-sama, why don't you and I make a deal?
家重様　私と取引しましょう
If you agree to keep secret what you saw here,
今宵　この場で見たものを秘密にする代わりに
I will not reveal your identity.
私はあなた様の素性を決して漏らしません
か　上方に放った御庭番が戻ってこないことと関わるなのか
Does this relate to the fact that the spies
we sent to Kyoto have not returned?
What lies beyond Kishuu?
紀州より先に何があるというのだ
お答えしかねます
I cannot answer that.
市民はもとより　幕府でも限られたものしか知らない機密
None of the citizens,
and only a select few of the
shogunate know this secret.
たとえ家重様といえども
Even you cannot be told.
I ask that you never return to
the Insect Magistrate's Office.
二度と蟲奉行所には立ち入らぬよう　お願い申し上げます
今宵の秘密は守ろう
I will keep this secret.
だが…
However,
every day, from now on,
I will come to see Jinbei.
俺はこれから毎日　仁兵衛に会いに来る
If that will do...
それでよいな
約束を　守っていただけるのであれば
If that will seal your promise.
私如きが　家重様に申し上げることはもう何もございません
There is nothing else that one like
I may ask of you, Ieshige-sama.
うん
I see...
そっか
仁兵衛君　次期将軍様に気に入られちゃったんだね
Jinbei-kun's befriended the next shogun.
不安材料は残るけど仕方ないか
I remain a bit uneasy, but I suppose it's all right.
You...
まったく　ちょっと蟲退治手伝ったからって
You think you're special for helping
a little against an insect?
調子に乗ってこんな所まで来るなんて
You think that means you can come here?
You intruder!
この不審者が
夏の風物詩　お江戸の花火がもうすぐだそうですね
Next Time
It's nearly time for the summer fireworks of Edo!
火鉢殿　この小さな花火玉二つも打ち上げるのですか
Will you be sending up these two
little fireworks, Hibachi-dono?
こりゃ　あたしの胸　エロ助が
Those are my breasts! You pervert!
Next time, on Mushibugyou:
次回　蟲奉行　「花のお江戸の夏の陣！！」
Summer War in Edo.
Summer War in Edo!!